<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Luna Ranjit</title><link>/lunaranjit/</link><description>Recent content on Luna Ranjit</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 17 Jul 2021 18:15:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/lunaranjit/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>What's New?</title><link>/lunaranjit/post/what-s-new/</link><pubDate>Sat, 17 Jul 2021 18:15:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/lunaranjit/post/what-s-new/</guid><description>Earlier this year, I was writing a lot, publishing sometimes. I was translating a book of poetry. I was developing a writing workshop. I had even applied for a writing grant, finally ready to fully accept my &amp;ldquo;writer&amp;rdquo; persona and let go of my &amp;ldquo;organizer&amp;rdquo; past. Friends and family members were getting vaccinated, at least the first dose, and the pandemic seemed to be getting under control. I was planning to launch this new website to share the new me.</description></item><item><title>Death By A Thousand Cuts: Newa Community &amp; The Caste System</title><link>/lunaranjit/post/death-by-a-thousand-cuts-newa-community-the-caste-system/</link><pubDate>Sat, 10 Jul 2021 18:15:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/lunaranjit/post/death-by-a-thousand-cuts-newa-community-the-caste-system/</guid><description>Caste-based discrimination is in news once again in Kathmandu, propelled by the rare courage shown by Rupa Sunar to not quietly accept the fact that an “upper caste” family in Kathmandu refused to rent her rooms just based on her caste. Indeed, Rupa Sunar is not the first person to be refused room rental because of their caste, nor the first person to take legal action against caste-based discrimination in room rental.</description></item><item><title>feminist manifesto</title><link>/lunaranjit/post/feminist-manifesto/</link><pubDate>Sun, 07 Mar 2021 18:15:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/lunaranjit/post/feminist-manifesto/</guid><description>not interested in feminism
seeped in racist thought
nor to fight for women’s rights
to become a corporate bot
don’t just shatter the glass ceiling
ignoring the sticky floor
if you came to save us
you can take the exit door
if you really believe in sisterhood
join us in our fight
no, we are not voiceless
just pass the goddam mic</description></item><item><title>the sprawl</title><link>/lunaranjit/post/the-sprawl/</link><pubDate>Wed, 24 Feb 2021 06:14:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/lunaranjit/post/the-sprawl/</guid><description>Looking down from the perch in Swayambhu
where tourists jostle with the locals for the view,
you see a multi-headed hydra
sprinting towards layers of
emerald hills guarding Kathmandu valley and the jagged
diamond peaks beyond, gobbling up
gold green fields along the way, guzzling
aquamarine ponds and lakes, spitting out
silver slivers of asphalt that crisscross
rivers’ and rivulets’ natural paths across the valley floor, belching
thick plumes of fumes that hang over the houses</description></item><item><title>Two Arcs of My Immigration Story</title><link>/lunaranjit/post/two-arcs-of-my-immigration-story/</link><pubDate>Thu, 24 Dec 2020 18:15:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/lunaranjit/post/two-arcs-of-my-immigration-story/</guid><description>I can tell my immigration story two different ways. One, I came here with $200 and two suitcases holding almost all of my worldly possessions. Two, I came here with a full scholarship to a rich liberal arts college. Both are true, and have shaped who I am and the way I view the world. Give or take a few details, my story is not that different from that of other immigrants who came to the U.</description></item><item><title>Voting in honor of my father</title><link>/lunaranjit/post/voting-in-honor-of-my-father/</link><pubDate>Tue, 03 Nov 2020 06:14:34 +0000</pubDate><guid>/lunaranjit/post/voting-in-honor-of-my-father/</guid><description>In the cool morning of November 8, 2016, I stood in line at the Joseph Pulitzer Intermediate School 145 in Jackson Heights, Queens, New York to cast the very first ballot of my life. I carefully filled out the bubbles on the ballot, thinking about my father. It had been exactly twenty-two months since he had passed.
I never got to vote while my father was alive because I was not old enough while living in Nepal, my country of birth, and I did not have U.</description></item><item><title>निर्णय निस्सन्तान जीवन यात्राको</title><link>/lunaranjit/post/%E0%A4%A8%E0%A4%BF%E0%A4%B0%E0%A5%8D%E0%A4%A3%E0%A4%AF-%E0%A4%A8%E0%A4%BF%E0%A4%B8%E0%A5%8D%E0%A4%B8%E0%A4%A8%E0%A5%8D%E0%A4%A4%E0%A4%BE%E0%A4%A8-%E0%A4%9C%E0%A5%80%E0%A4%B5%E0%A4%A8-%E0%A4%AF%E0%A4%BE%E0%A4%A4%E0%A5%8D%E0%A4%B0%E0%A4%BE%E0%A4%95%E0%A5%8B/</link><pubDate>Wed, 02 Sep 2020 06:14:34 +0000</pubDate><guid>/lunaranjit/post/%E0%A4%A8%E0%A4%BF%E0%A4%B0%E0%A5%8D%E0%A4%A3%E0%A4%AF-%E0%A4%A8%E0%A4%BF%E0%A4%B8%E0%A5%8D%E0%A4%B8%E0%A4%A8%E0%A5%8D%E0%A4%A4%E0%A4%BE%E0%A4%A8-%E0%A4%9C%E0%A5%80%E0%A4%B5%E0%A4%A8-%E0%A4%AF%E0%A4%BE%E0%A4%A4%E0%A5%8D%E0%A4%B0%E0%A4%BE%E0%A4%95%E0%A5%8B/</guid><description>“महिनावारी भनेको गर्भ रहन नसकेको डिम्बको आँसु हो” — केटाकेटी हुँदा रेडियोमा सुनेको यो वाक्य म अझै भुल्न सक्दिन। सानोमा त यसलाई नै सत्य मानियो। तर पछि प्रश्न उठ्न थाल्यो — के महिलाको जीवनको अस्तित्व गर्भाशयमा अडिएको छ? के गर्भवती हुन नसक्ने वा गर्भाशय नै नभएका महिला नै होइनन्?
म एक विवाहिता महिला जसले बच्चा नजन्माउने निर्णय गरेको छ। पन्ध्र वर्ष अघि हामीले जीवन यात्रा शुरु गर्दा हाम्रो उद्देश्य, मूल्य, मान्यता, पैसा प्रतिको धारणाका साथसाथै बच्चा जन्माउने कि नजन्माउने भन्ने बिषयमा निक्कै छलफल गर्यौं। हाम्रा तर्क फरक फरक भए पनि हामी एउटै निष्कर्षमा पुग्यौं — बच्चा नजन्माउने। हामी परिवारबाट टाढा विदेशमा बस्थ्यौं। हाम्रो सपोर्ट सिस्टम थिएन त्यति बेला। हामीलाई वंश बढाउनु पर्छ भन्ने पनि लाग्दैन। हामीले निर्णय गर्यौं कि यदि पछि बच्चा चाहिन्छ नै जस्तो लाग्यो भने अडप्ट गर्ने। हामीले बेला बेलामा यो निर्णयलाई केलाएका छौं र निष्कर्ष अझै त्यहि नै छ — बच्चा बिनाको जीवन नै हाम्रो लागि सहि हो।</description></item><item><title>they come in pairs</title><link>/lunaranjit/post/they-come-in-pairs/</link><pubDate>Thu, 30 Apr 2020 18:15:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/lunaranjit/post/they-come-in-pairs/</guid><description>statistics says
on average
two coffins
come back to Nepal
every day
statistics does not say
those wooden boxes
also carry
shattered dreams
lost loves
forfeited futures
vanished hopes
statistics does not care
if anyone will remember
the young men who fly away
filled with aspiration and trepidation
who come back as numbers
in pairs
every single day</description></item><item><title>More than Mangoes</title><link>/lunaranjit/post/more-than-mangoes/</link><pubDate>Mon, 27 Apr 2020 18:15:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/lunaranjit/post/more-than-mangoes/</guid><description>a short food memoir
When I first started writing about home, I fell straight into the tired South Asian American trope and wrote about nostalgia for mango juice running down my arms in the summer. I do love mangoes, but nostalgia for them was a stretch. But that’s what I had been reading from people who looked the most like me, and that’s what came out. I was trying to repackage someone else’s memory as my own.</description></item><item><title>Compassion in the time of Covid-19</title><link>/lunaranjit/post/compassion-in-the-time-of-covid-19/</link><pubDate>Tue, 07 Apr 2020 18:15:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/lunaranjit/post/compassion-in-the-time-of-covid-19/</guid><description>A few days ago, it was reported that the President of Nepal expressed concern about the Nepalis in the U.S. in her conversation with the Nepali Ambassador, as she did with other envoys in countries with large numbers of Nepalis. A lot of “progressive Nepalis,” including a few friends, jumped on her for not caring about the migrant workers stuck at the Indian border and only caring about those in the affluent country.</description></item><item><title>Year of Buying Nothing</title><link>/lunaranjit/post/year-of-buying-nothing/</link><pubDate>Mon, 23 Dec 2019 18:15:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/lunaranjit/post/year-of-buying-nothing/</guid><description>Holiday season is upon us, and the festivities are accompanied by shopping sprees on adrenaline. Consumerism really seems to have become a new religion with the Black Friday and Cyber Monday as its holy days. In the past, I too would have gotten caught up in the frenzy. This year, however, I am surviving relatively unscathed as I am halfway through a year-long experiment of buying nothing but the essentials. I am not completely immune as friends and family members around me are still participating.</description></item><item><title>Luna Ranjit</title><link>/lunaranjit/author/luna-ranjit/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/lunaranjit/author/luna-ranjit/</guid><description/></item></channel></rss>